A Guide to the Ball Family Papers, 1680-1785
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Ball Family Papers, 1680-1785
The Library of Virginia
23554
12 leaves and 47 pages
Ball Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 29 June 1950, of Frank Taylor of Fredericksburg, Virginia, through George H. S. King of Fredericksburg.
Biographical Information
Born about 1615, William Ball emigrated to Virginia and became a prosperous landowner in Lancaster County, Virginia. He served as a justice, a colonel of the militia, and as a delegate to the House of Burgesses. He fathered four children, including William Ball (1641-1694). This William Ball had nine children, including William Ball (ca. 1674-1744). He married Hannah Heale (d. ca. 1744) and they had 6 children, including William Ball (ca. 1700-1741). He married his cousin Margaret Ball (ca. 1702-1783), the daughter of his uncle Richard Ball (ca. 1675-1726) 17 February 1723/4. They had 6 children, including William Ball (d. 1760), who had 2 children, including Dr. William Ball (d. 1785).
Scope and Content
Papers, 1680-1785, of the Ball family of Lancaster County, Virginia, consisting of wills, 1680-1785, of William Ball (1615-1680), Richard Ball (ca. 1675-1726), Margaret Ball (ca. 1702-1783), and William Ball (d. 1785), all of Lancaster County; inventories, 1727-1773, of the estates of Richard Ball, William Ball, Jr. (1700-1741), John Ball (d. 1772), and an unidentified estate; deeds, 1733-1758, for property in Lancaster County and slaves; letters, 1764 and 1780, discussing the property of Margaret Ball; depositions, 1775-1782, concerning the purchase of slaves from the estate of William Ball, and concerning crops made on the estate of John Ball; legal opinions, 1779 and no date, concerning the estate of Mary Ball, and concerning a deed between Margaret Ball and William Ball; a list, no date, of slaves from an unidentified estate; and Ball family genealogical notes.
Contents List
- Will, dated 5 October 1680 and recorded 10 November 1680, of William Ball (1615-1680) of Lancaster County.
- Will, recorded 8 February 1726/7, of Richard Ball (ca. 1675-1726) of Lancaster County.
- Inventory, recorded 9 August 1727, of the estate of Richard Ball.
- Deed, dated 12 May 1733, for 1/2 acre in Lancaster County from Hopkins Wilder to Lawrence Blade, both of Lancaster County, subsequent assignments dated 29 June 1742 and 22 October 1745.
- Inventory, dated 4 October 1742, of the estate of William Ball Jr. (ca. 1700-1741).
- Deed, dated 8 May 1747, for land and slaves from Margaret Ball (ca. 1702-1783) to William Ball (d. 1785), both of Lancaster County.
- Ball family genealogical chart, 24 August 1748.
- Deed, recorded in general court 27 October 1758, for 50 acres in Lancaster County from Margaret Ball to William Ball.
- Letter, 30 October 1764, from David Boyd to Margaret Ball concerning property inherited from her husband.
- Deposition, 1 August 1775, of James Newby (1723-1791) concerning the purchase of slaves by John Lee of Essex County, Virginia, from the estate of William Ball.
- Deposition, 1 August 1775, of Richard Ball (b. 1732) concerning the purchase of slaves by John Lee of Essex County, Virginia, from the estate of William Ball.
- Inventory, recorded 19 July 1773 in Lancaster County and 27 July 1773 in Fauquier County, Virginia, of the estate of John Ball (d. 1772).
- Legal opinion, 15 April 1779, of David Boyd concerning the estate of Mary Ball.
- Legal opinion, 22 December 1779, of Edmund Randolph concerning the estate of Mary Ball.
- Legal opinion, 22 December 1779, of Edmund Randolph concerning the estate of Mary Ball.
- Letter, 21 April 1780, from Margaret Ball to William Ball concerning her property.
- Deposition, 22 September 1782, by Norman Utterback, overseer, concerning crops made on the estate of John Ball.
- Will, dated 21 June 1777 and recorded 16 October 1783, of Margaret Ball.
- Will, dated 17 June 1785 and recorded 22 July 1785, of William Ball.
- Inventory, no date, of an unidentified estate.
- List, no date, of slaves of an unidentified estate.
- Legal opinion, no date, concerning a deed between Margaret Ball and William Ball.
- Genealogical notes, no date, on the Ball family.
- Will, no date, of Margaret Ball.